翻译&校对｜陆爱夏
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
夏洛特·兰普林
汤姆·康特奈
45周年
过来 马克斯
Come on, Max.
- 早上好 默瑟夫人  - 克里斯啊
- Morning, Mrs Mercer.  - Oh, Chris.
今天起的很早嘛
You're early this morning.
大清早孩子就吵醒我了
I've got the twins waking me up at the crack of dawn.
老天啊 我完全忘了
Oh, my God, I completely forgot.
- 恭喜你  - 同喜同喜
- Congratulations.  - Cheers.
- 夫妻俩还应付得来吧  - 有太多事要做了
- How are you both coping?  - It's a hell of a lot of work, that's to be sure.
我同意
I don't doubt it a second.
你会没事的 你年轻力壮
But you'll be fine. You were always a capable young man.
很高兴吧
You must be getting excited.
- 是这周六吧  - 别说了 我还有很多活要做呢
- Saturday, isn't it?  - Don't remind me. So much work to do.
小事一桩
Yeah, it'll be fine.
- 祝你好运  - 谢谢
- Good luck.  - Thank you.
我真心为你们感到高兴
And I'm really over the moon for both of you.
- 谢谢 默瑟女士  - 别见外 叫我凯特就行
- Thank you, Mrs Mercer.  - Kate. Call me Kate.
这可不是学校 不用那么礼貌
We're not at school any more.
我会的
Will do.
[The Platters 为美国黑人摇滚乐队]
[代表作《Only You》、《Smoke Gets in Your Eyes》]
你觉得Platters的歌怎么样
What do you think of that Platters song?
- 什么  - The Platters的歌
- The what?  - The Platters song.
干嘛用的
What for?
第一支舞啊
First dance.
不觉得用婚礼上的那首歌有点过时了吗
Or think it's a bit naff to have the same song we had at our wedding?
不觉得 那歌很好听
No. Lovely song.
- 我很喜欢  - 我知道
- I've always liked it.  - Yeah, I know.
♫ 人们曾经问我怎知 ♫
♪ Asked me how I knew ♪
♫ 我的爱情意真挚 ♫
♪ My true love was true ♪
这什么  - 一封信
- What is it?  - A letter.
我看得出来 谁写的
Yes, I know, but who from?
- 德语写的  - 是啊
- It's in German.  - Yeah.
说了点啥
What's it say?
好多词我都不记得了 但…
Well, I can't remember the verbs as well as the nouns, but...
我觉得是他们找到她了
But I think it says they've found her.
找到谁了
Found who?
她的尸体
Well, her body, anyway.
别吓我 杰夫 谁啊
God. who? Geoff.
他们找到卡蒂亚了
T-They've found Katya.
你知道我在说谁吧
Y-You know who I'm talking about, don't you?
当然
Of course.
我清楚记得跟你说过她的事
Cos, I-I remember telling you, clear as day.
我当然记得 都这么久了
Of course I remember. I mean, it was a long time ago.
是啊 我就知道跟你说过我的卡蒂亚
Yeah, I-I know I told you about my Katya.
她在那呆了五十多年 和放进冷藏室一样
She's been there over 50 years, like something in the freezer.
现在他们找到她了
Now they've found her.
[图伦人是欧洲发现的史前人类]
像在瑞典沼泽里发现图伦人一样
L-Like that, er, Tollund Man in the Swedish bog.
其实是在丹麦发现的
Well, Danish, actually.
- 啊  - 教程上有说
- Hm?  - It was on the curriculum for years.
我给三年级的学生讲过
I taught it to the third-formers.
我给你再倒点茶
I'll make some more tea.
我得要本字典
Yeah, I'm going to need a dictionary.
我不记得放哪儿了
I-I don't know where to look.
看看那些塑料盒里有没有
Why don't you check in the plastic boxes?
没有 除了些DIY的书
Nothing. Nothing but do-it-yourself books.
就是这本
That's it.
谢谢
Ah, thank you.
雪完全融化了
You see, what's happened is the snow has completely melted.
剩下的都是冰
All that's left is the ice.
他们就是这样找到她的
A-And that's how they found her.
- 你什么意思  - 她还在那里
- What do you mean?  - Well, she's still there.
- 在冰里面  - 没错
- In the ice?  - Yeah.
可能在下游 但水很清澈
Way down, I'm sure, but the water is very pure up there.
肯定是这样 他们就发现了她
It must be, so they can see her.
- 他们把她弄出来了吗  - 还没
- Well, haven't they taken her out?  - Not yet.
为什么
Why not?
凯特 她可是在瑞士的冰川里
Well, she's in a glacier in the Swiss mountains, Kate.
没那么容易
It can't be that easy.
没有上去的路
There are no roads up there.
那他们怎么确定是她的呢
So, how do they know it's her?
我觉得 不一定是她
I mean, it might not be her at all.
从发现她的位置来看 也就是个猜想吧
Well, they've made an assumption, I suppose, from where they found her.
他们可能是通过衣物辨别出来的
Maybe they can tell from what she's wearing.
从衣物
From what she's wearing?
对 对 那些冰岛的飞行员 我记得
Oh, yeah, yeah, th-those, er, airmen in...lceland, I-I think it was,
他们的衣服就保存完好
they were perfectly preserved,
我不记得了
Oh, I don't remember that.
是的 我看过关于这个的纪录片
Yes. I saw a documentary on it.
由于快速冷冻的原因 衣物还保持死亡前的样子
They were the same as when they died because of how quickly they froze.
你觉得是这么回事
And you think that's what's happened?
我不知道 但我能想
Well, I don't know, but you can imagine.
我可不这么想 都过去那么久了
Not sure it works like that. Not after all this time.
那得多奇怪啊
How strange would that be, though?
她的模样一点没变
She'll look like she did in 1962.
而我却是这般模样
And I look like this.
怎么了
What is it?
凯特 别生气
Er, don't be cross, Kate.
我去抽支烟
I'm going to have a smoke.
- 你还好吧  - 我没事
- Are you all right?  - Fine.
把药和这个都吃了
Please eat this. And take your pills.
他们问我要不要去趟瑞士
Th-They've asked if I want to go to Switzerland.
何出此言
Why would they ask that?
去看尸体
Well, to see the body.
- 什么时候  - 很快吧
- When?  - Soon, I suppose.
- 你不会是想去吧  - 我不知道
- You aren't thinking of going?  - Don't know.
这可是去瑞士啊
All the way to Switzerland?
也不是很远
It's not that far.
有伦敦去瑞士的航班
There are fights from Stansted.
没错 但也很远了
Yeah, but it's far enough,
- 你觉得我不应该去  - 说真心话
- You don't think I should?  - Honestly?
是的
Well, no.
我不知道你去了干嘛
I don't see the point.
- 我们周六还有派对呢  - 我也不是现在去
- Plus we've got the party on Saturday.  - I wasn't thinking of going now.
- 我现在不走  - 但还是
- I-I wouldn't go now.  - Yeah, but still.
我可不敢想你去爬什么山
I don't like the idea of you climbing a big bloody mountain.
应该不会去爬山的
Well, I don't think it would come to that.
你连和我在河边散步都不去
You don't like going for a walk with me on the Broads
- 那里那么平坦  - 我知道
- and that's as flat as a pancake.  - I know.
凯特 我说了 我不会去爬山的
Like I said, Kate, it wouldn't come to that.
但是…
But still...
- 你不是要去镇上吗  - 我可以再安排
- Don't you have to go into town?  - Oh, I can rearrange.
别 你快去吧
No. Y-you should go.
我就是有点受惊
It's been a bit of a shock, that's all.
我没事的
But I'm fine.
- 你确定  - 我确定
- Are you sure?  - Yeah, positive.
空空的 看起来确实不同
Oh, It looks different, all empty.
这里通常是放桌子的
Well, this is where the tables are usually placed.
贵宾席在这 大伙都看得见这
The top one over there, so that everyone can see you.
我们不需要贵宾席 但还是谢谢
We won't be having a top table, but thank you.
真的
Really?
这种场合应该有贵宾席
A top table is so lovely at an event like this.
你们可是屋里的焦点
The two of you as a focal point of the room.
我们不是想重现婚礼现场
We're not trying to recreate the wedding.
就是个聚会
It's just a party.
那是自然 尊重您的选择
Yes, well, it's your choice, of course.
我还是得说 在这里庆祝纪念日是明智之选
I will say, though, it's a wonderful place, location-wise, for an anniversary.
四十周年了吧
It's your 40th, isn't it?
四十五周年
45th.
四十五周年庆倒是很特别
That's an unusual one to celebrate.
四十周年的时候我丈夫病了 我们就重新安排了
My husband was ill and our 40th was cancelled, so we had to rearrange.
那我就得把聚会做的更加特别
Well, I must try and make this one super-special, then, mustn't I?
来这办纪念活动再合适不过了
And this really is a great venue for such an event.
充满历史的印记
So full of history, you see?
如同一段良缘
Like a good marriage.
[特拉法尔加海战为英法两国的海上大战，最终英方取胜]
您知道庆祝特拉法尔加海战胜利活动就是在这里办的吗
Did you know that the Trafalgar Ball was held here?
是的 你助手告诉我了
Yes, your assistant told me.
在一八〇五年
It was in 1805.
你能想象当时壮观的场景吗
Can you imagine how incredible that must have been?
大家盛装出席 庆祝伟大的胜利
Everyone here, dressed in their finest, celebrating such an achievement.
[霍雷肖·纳尔逊为英国海军总司令，海战英方指挥者]
纳尔逊不是死了吗
Wasn't Nelson killed?
最后还不是赢了
But the battle was won.
难道不值得庆祝吗
And that has to be worth celebrating, doesn't it?
我们婚礼上有贵宾席 但我们都不喜欢
We had a table at our wedding, a top table, but we didn't like it at all.
我丈夫觉得这是资本家的坏传统
My husband thought it a horribly bourgeois tradition.
去看看开胃菜菜单吧
Shall we have a look at the canapé list?
行
Er, yes, indeed.
稍等一下
I'll be right back.
不着急
No rush.
这是杰夫和凯特家 请留言
You have reached Geoff and Kate. Please leave a message.
《我的秋天来了》
"My Autumn's Done Come"
你许久没听这歌了
You haven't listened to this for a long time.
- 感觉如何  - 还好
- How are you feeling?  - I'm fine.
你手指怎么了
What have you done to your finger?
噢 我想修抽水马桶 不小心切到大拇指
Oh, yeah, I was, er...trying to mend the lavatory and, er, well, I cut me thumb.
修好了吗
Did you manage to fix it?
我觉得得换个浮球阀
It needs a new ballcock, I think.
- 之前我打了电话  - 你留言了吗
- Tried calling earlier on.  - Did you leave a message?
没 就是想看看你怎么样
No, I just wanted to check you were all right.
好
Right.
[索伦·奥贝·克尔凯郭尔为丹麦基督教思想家，存在主义先驱]
- 你在看什么  - 克尔凯郭尔
- What are you reading?  - Kierkegaard.
天啊 怎么又看起他的书了
Gracious, are you having a go at that again?
那本书你有三个版本
You know, you have three editions of that book,
哪本你看到过第三章
and I don't think you've got past chapter two in any of them.
今天真奇怪
Yeah, it's been an odd day.
是啊
It sure has.
我呆在家里
I just, er...stayed at home,
捣鼓浮球阀
you know, grappling with the ballcock.
你说得对
But y-you're right.
我都不出去走走
I hardly go walking any more.
今天天气不错 所以我出去了一趟
And it was a nice day, so off I went.
- 那你去了哪儿  - 就是去村庄那儿
- So, where did you go?  - Just to the village.
去买烟
To buy cigarettes?
你以为我鼻子出问题了
I haven't lost my sense of smell,you know?
我可不想我们重拾吸烟的毛病
I just don't want us to start smoking again.
我不会的
No, I-I won't, I won't.
我保证
I promise.
行 继续说
OK. Go on.
我在村庄里 也不懂发生了什么
So, I was in the village,and I don't know what happened
社区中心的那个种族主义者
but that racist from the community centre...
桑德拉·威尔金斯
Sandra Wilkins.
对 就是她
Yeah, her.
她走到我面前来
She came up to me, right up to me face,
一直问我有没有事
and she kept asking me if I was all right.
我说没事 她就是不信我
And when I said I was,she wouldn't believe me.
我什么都没做
And...l wasn't doing anything.
我就坐在鸭池旁的板凳上
Nothing. Just sitting on the bench by the duck pond,
不招惹别人 呼吸新鲜空气
minding me own business and getting some air,
包好了
All done.
我保证 我什么也没做
All I was doing, I promise.
我相信你
I believe you.
这女人太奇怪了
She's a dreadful woman.
别理她
Just ignore her.
还行吧
Is it all right?
好吃 很好
Oh, it's great. Great.
还要酒吗
A drop more?
好 谢谢
Mm, thank you.
- 怎么了  - 没什么
- What?  - Nothing.
- 我想跟你说点事  - 说吧
- There's something I want to tell you.  - OK.
我觉得我跟你说过
You know, I-I feel sure I've told you before,
很久以前的事了 我可能记错了
but it was a long time ago,so, I mean, I could be wrong.
- 说吧  - 嗯
- OK, go on.- Yeah.
我是她的近亲
Um, I-I was her next of kin.
你什么意思
What do you mean?
法律上来说
Well, officially.
我是她的近亲 凯特 我以前跟你说过
I-I was her next of kin.I'm sure I told you this before, Kate.
这种事我肯定会记得的
I think I would remember my husband being another woman's next of kin.
为什么  - 什么为什么
- Why?  - Why what?
为什么你会是她的近亲
Well, why were you her next of kin?
因为他们觉得我们结婚了
Because they thought we were married.
- 谁觉得  - 官方 群众
- Who did?  - The authorities. People.
为什么他们会这么想
What made them think that?
是我们告诉他们的
We-We told them we were.
你们没结婚吧
You weren't, though?
当然没有
Oh, no, no, no. No, h-hell, no.
都是假装的 这样我们就能住在他们家里了
We just had to pretend, so people would let us stay in their houses,
凯特 那时候情况不一样 意外之后…
Different in those days, Kate,and then after the accident...
你说的都是实话
You're not lying to me?
凯特 她手上戴着戒指
No. Kate, she wore a ring on her finger.
一个小小的木头戒指 橡木做的 和幕环一样
It was a small wooden ring, like a curtain ring, made of oak.
这些你还记得
Funny you'd remember that.
都是假的
Well, it wasn't real.
杰夫 这些你直接跟我说就行
OK, you could've...you could've just told me, Geoff.
我以为我说了
I thought I had.
就算我没说 这事…
If I hadn't, well, it's hardly, er...
这些事很难开口…一个貌美的新女友
The sort of thing you tell... your beautiful new girlfriend, is it?
那倒是
I suppose not.
我想… 上楼洗个澡
I think I'm going to have a... go upstairs and have a bath.
明天还有很多事要做
I've got lots to do tomorrow.
- 你没事吧  - 没事
- Are you sure you're all right?  - Yes. Yes.
我真的没事
Yeah. really, I am.
那个时候我们都没在一起 我生什么气
I can hardly be cross with something that happened before we existed, can I?
但是…
Still...
可以抱一下吗
I suppose a cuddle's out of the question.
都不觉得在场的人是我
It doesn't even feel like it was me that was there.
明白我的意思吗
Do you know what I mean?
你去那里呆了多久
How long had you been up there?
大概六到七周吧
Oh, six or seven weeks, I suppose.
感觉还要再久点
It seemed a lot longer.
开始的时候我们有地图
We had a map, er, to start with.
画的根本就不对
It was so bloody unreliable.
我们还是到了
I've still got it somewhere.
我们到了大山高地
Yeah, we were getting higher into the mountains
我觉得我们最好还是找个人
and I decided it would be best if we found someone,
带我们去意大利边界
y-you know, to help us get to the Italian border.
- 向导  - 也不能叫向导吧
- A guide?  - Yeah, wasn't really a guide.
[杰克 · 凯鲁亚克，美国著名小说家，代表作《在路上》]
黑黢黢的小混蛋自以为是杰克 · 凯鲁亚克
This swarthy little bastard who thought he was Jack Kerouac.
- 你不是一直都讨厌凯鲁亚克吗  - 对
- You always did hate Kerouac.  - Yes, I did.
你是嫉妒吧
Maybe you were jealous.
- 嫉妒杰克 · 凯鲁亚克吗  - 嫉妒向导
- What, of Jack Kerouac?  - Of the guide.
他和她调情吗
Was he flirting with her?
他们有用语言
Well, they did have, er...the language.
我德语不太好 他们说话还带口音
My German, it wasn't that great, what with its accent.
他们一直在笑
They laughed a lot.
他说的笑话 我一个没听懂
He was forever making these jokes. I didn't get.
- 你可喜欢这样  - 是啊
- Oh, God, you wouldn't like that.  - No, I didn't.
他们走在前面 远超必要的距离
They were walking up ahead, more than they needed to perhaps,
我就让他们这样做 我也不懂
or...maybe I just let them, I don't know.
我们走在岩石旁的小路上
We were on a track round this rock,
冰川就在我们右边的低洼处
and the glacier was on the right, below us.
很远的地方
Way down.
非常美丽
Beautiful thing, it was.
凯特 你会喜欢那里的美景
You'd love the landscape out there, Kate.
- 说真的  - 我也觉得
- You really would.  - Yeah, I'm sure.
拐弯的时候 他们就不见了
They were out of sight, round the corner,
我最后只听见她的笑声
and the last sound but one that I heard was her laughter.
真烦心
And, Christ, did it annoy me?
可然后 传来一声尖叫
But then, there was a scream.
不是很大声
It wasn't a loud scream, neither.
我感觉是 受到惊吓 从肺里喷出来的空气
Sort of outpouring of air from her lungs, from the shock, I suppose.
粗哑低沉
It was low and guttural.
不像她原本的嗓音
Not like her voice, which was soft, higher-pitched.
天 太恐怖了
God, that's just horrible.
然后呢
And then what?
然后就没了
That was it, really.
我到的时候 她已经不见了
When I got there, she'd gone.
指路的看着那窟窿
And Kerouac was looking down this hole.
一个裂缝
A fissure.
没错 应该这么叫 岩石上一条小小的缝
Yeah, a fissure, I suppose you'd call it, like a narrow, narrow crack in the rock.
你记得苏格兰的那条吗
D-Do you remember that one in Scotland?
- 我记得  - 和那个一样
- Yeah, I do.  - Yeah. Well, it was like that one.
- 懂了  - 就是更深点
- Yeah.  - Only much deeper.
指路的就站在那里
And Kerouac was just standing there.
他的脸都变黄了
His face, oddly enough,it looked almost yellow.
她金黄色的
Was she blonde?
- 什么  - 她是金黄色的头发
- Sorry?- Did she have blond hair?
不是 她头发深色
Oh, no. no. She had dark hair.
和我的一样咯
Like mine, then.
不是像现在这样
I mean, not now.
对 和你的一样
Yeah, like yours.
她多大当时
How old was she?
她比我大两岁 当时是六二年
She was two years older than me,and that was '62.
那她就二十七岁
Yeah, so she was about 27.
那年我妈妈去世了
My mum died that year.
- 真的  - 对啊
- Did she?  - Yeah. Mm.
- 我不知道为什么我会觉得很好玩  - 好玩
- I don't know why that's funny but it is.  - Funny?
那时我们还不认识
Well, we didn't know each other then,you and I,
可我们都经历了十分不愉快的事
but we were both going through something really unpleasant, and...
而我们在一起这么多年了 也没聊过这些
And yet we never talked about it in all the years that we've known each other.
- 从来没有  - 是啊
- Never.  - No. Never have.
我累了
I'm tired.
那我关灯了
Shall I tum off the light?
好的
Yeah.
我也很累了
I'm quite tired, too.
星期二
来
Come on.
Yeah, boy! Come on!
真乖 好样的
Come on! Good boy.
今天起的很早嘛
You're up early this morning.
我想和你一起去镇里 你觉得怎么样
Yeah, I thought I might come into town with you, if you don't mind.
好啊 来吧
No. Of course I don't mind.
我想去买个新的浮球阀
Yeah, I-I want to go to Thorns,get a new ballcock.
可以啊
On, good.
凯特 我图书馆卡还能用吗
Do you think my library card will still be valid, Kate?
- 应该可以吧  - 如果有时间 我想去趟图书馆
- I don't see why not.  - I might pop in there if there's time.
随意翻看一下书
Have a bit of a browse.
- 可以一起吃个午饭  - 不错
- We could have some lunch.- Yeah, great.
那我去忙了
Well, er, I'll just go do what I have to do.
准备好了 叫我就行
Give a shout when you're ready,
好
OK.
我要去联系下花商 还有点其他的事
I've got to call the florist and one or two things.
图书馆有关于气候变化的书吗
Do you think the library will have anything on climate change?
- 什么的书  - 气候变化
- On what?  - Climate change.
- 不好意思来晚了  - 不要紧
- Sorry I'm late.  - All right.
- 买了吗  - 买什么
- Did you get the thing?  - What thing?
- 浮球阀呀  - 他们需要订购
- The ballcock.  - Er, they have to order it.
几天后再来取
I'll pick it up in a few days.
想吃什么
What do you want to eat?
我们要多为环境着想
We've got to think a lot more about the environment.
- 我们有循环利用  - 真的
- Well, we recycle.  - Do we?
- 我有在尝试  - 我们应该这么做
- Yeah. Well, I try to, anyway.  - Well, we should.
你可以去收拾狗罐头 然后放进对应的垃圾箱
You're welcome to clean out the dog cans and put them in the right bins,
因为环境原因 冰川比我们想象的融的快
Because these glaciers, they're melting a Iot, more than people imagined,
- 海平面不会下降  - 水会流向某些地方的吧
- and the water's just not coming down.- It's got to go somewhere.
不会的 水渗透进岩石层 它不断变大变大
No, it's saturating into the rock beneath,and it's building up and up and up.
- 就像…  - 和大坝一样
- L-Like...- Like a dam.
对 然后耐心等待… 直到…
Like a dam, yeah. it's waiting,waiting, waiting, and then...
小心点 没有任何警告
Careful. No warning.
海啸降临 卷走所有的一切
Come down like a tsunami,wipe out everything in its path.
学校 教堂 喝咖啡的人
Schools, churches, people in cafes drinking their coffee.
还有商店里摆弄布谷鸟钟的老头
Old men in shops tinkering with their cuckoo clocks.
要是他没被发现 海啸也会带她出现
And if they hadn't found her,that's when she'd have come down,
以及碎石瓦砾
with all the rock and debris.
那时候我们都死绝了
We'll be long dead by then.
把书拿开
Put your book away.
噢 好
Oh, yeah.
- 凯特 干嘛不接我电话  - 不是故意的
- You screening my calls, Kate?- Not really.
- 莎莉 嗨  - 你好 杰夫
- Sally!- Hi, Geoff.
这个 我最喜欢了
That's my favourite one, there.
可以了 妈 我都看烦了
OK, Mum. I think it's enough now. It's getting really boring.
- 我为我孙子骄傲  - 莎莉 我来看看小查理
- I'm proud of my grandson.- Sally, I want to have a look at Chariey.
太可爱了
These are so lovely.
照片也很美
And the photos are really beautiful.
- 是吧  - 莎莉要成为一名摄影师
- Aren't they?  - Sally's going to be a photographer.
我没有 我就是在上夜校 只是喜欢而已
I'm not. I'm just taking an evening course, just for the fun of it.
没什么值得一提的
It's nothing grand.
- 说不定就有戏呢  - 很难说
- But it might lead to something.- Or it might not.
我三个月前开始的
I took it up about three months ago.
尤克里里真是个值得一学的乐器 什么音乐都能演奏
It's a good instrument to Iearn,You can play anything on the ukulele.
[乔治·福姆比 英国演员 时常弹奏尤克里里(夏威夷四弦琴)]
不仅仅乔治·福姆比会弹 你也知道 我不喜欢他
It's not just George Formby, which is good. Because, as you know, I always hated him.
网络实在太棒了
The Internet is absolutely brilliant.
你去一个叫justinguitar的网站
If you go to a guy called justinguitar.com,
会免费教你弹吉他
he actually teaches guitar,but it's all free.
也开始教尤克里里了
He's started, er,teaching ukulele as well.
再见 玩得开心
See you later. Have a nice time.
好的 再见
All right, see you later.
杰夫不太想去酒吧
I don't think...l don't think Geoff wanted to go to the pub.
不然他就得和我们一起逛街
It's either that or he comes shopping with us.
我们可以一起去酒吧啊
We could have gone to the pub,all of us.
看看他白天喝酒的样子
Know what he's like with daytime drinking.
他不会有事的
Oh, he'll be all right,
这也是发泄的好机会
Anyway, it gives him a chance to vent.
- 发泄什么  - 说你啊
- About what?- About you.
妈
Mum!
不说你 也要说派对吧
Not about you as such,but about the party.
你这是什么意思 发泄一下派对
What do you mean about...vent about the party?
想到乔治在我们四十周年前的态度
When I think how awful George was before our 40th,
我差点就和他离婚了
I was that close to divorcing him.
别理我妈
Ignore her.
选好礼服了吗 喜欢什么样的
So, what's going to happen with your dress? What would you like?
那我还要不要办派对啊
So, should I not be having a party?
当然要
Of course you should,
对我们压力都很大
It is a lot of pressure for both of us.
再说我也不会喜欢派对
And I hate parties anyway,at the best of times.
我连生日都不庆祝
I mean, I never even celebrate my birthday.
不能这么想 派对得办
No. no, no, no, no, You have to.
说来也奇怪
I mean, that's the strange thing.
乔治态度是很差 但你记得他在派对上的表现吗
George was awful, but then do you remember him at the actual party?
他哭得多厉害
How much he cried?
不仅是在讲话的时候
And not only during the speeches.
是啊 他很贴心
Yeah, he was very sweet.
所以说派对很重要
That's why these things are important.
让丈夫都去抹眼泪
What, to make our husbands cry
不止丈夫 是所有男人
Not just husbands, all men.
伤心的总是他们
It's always them that break first.
莎莉的婚礼 查理的洗礼
Sally's wedding, Charley's christening.
我们没崩溃 是因为我们知道这些事的重要性
We hold it together cos we already know how important these things are.
可杰夫不爱哭啊
Geoff is not much of a crier.
结婚的时候他肯定哭了
I bet he cried at your wedding.
记不得了
I don't remember.
男人的世界观和女人的就是不一样
I think they just see the world different from us.
要是进化能让
If some twist of evolution
男人沉迷于讣告与遗产
that needs men to be obsessed by their obituaries, their legacies,
是我们 在他们死于沮丧前
then maybe it's ours to nudge them into realising what's really important
让他们认识到什么才是关键
before they kill themselves,you know, with the disappointment.
早上好
Morning.
我打了会儿盹
I nodded off.
你觉得莎莉的照片如何
What did you think of Sally's photos?
- 啊  - 莎莉的照片
- Mm?- Sally's photos.
她眼光不错
I think she's got a very good eye.
是啊 是啊
Oh, sure. Yeah. Mm.
有时候真遗憾屋里没什么照片
I sometimes think it's a shame not to have more photos around the house.
那我们就挂起来
We could put some up.
可我们没什么照片
Yeah. but we don't have any. Not really.
不像Lena家的照片墙一样
I mean, not like Lena does with her wall display.
可能是因为他们子孙满堂吧
I suppose it's because they've got children and grandchildren, and...
我们可能没意识到拍照的重要性吧
I guess we didn't see the point of taking pictures of ourselves.
是不是有点自大了
Would have been a bit vain.
以前你说那些总是拍照的人
You used to say that everybody taking pictures all the time
是在阻止别人享受
stopped anyone having any fun.
- 是吗  - 是你说的
- Did I?- You did.
听起来像我说出的话
Sounds like something I'd say.
以前你也有个照相机
You had a camera, once.
- 对 一台雅西卡  - 对 雅西卡
- Yeah, a Yashica.- Mm, a Yashica.
我还留着呢
Yeah, I've still got it.
在阁楼里放着
It's in the loft.
现在老了 感觉真是遗憾
Now that we're older, though,it...it's a shame.
那你想拍点什么呢
What would you want photos of?
马克斯还是小狗时的样子
Max when he was a pup.
还有之前的泰莎
Tessa before him
还有你 在装修的时候 把钉子扎进你手里
You when you were decorating Clitheroe and you hammered that nail into your hand.
你拍那个干什么
You want a photograph of that?
你明白我的意思
Oh, you know what I mean.
那是我们第一个家
It was our first house.
是啊
It was.
那是我离家之后的第一个家
Yeah, it was my first home since leaving home,
离开父母 离开我父亲
since leaving my parents, leaving my father.
当时我们没意识到
I suppose we don't realise at the time
那些记忆…
but those memories...
十分珍贵
..they're the things, aren't they?
我想拍你在利兹购物中心的样子
I'd want a picture of you at the Leeds Mecca.
那是我们相遇的地方
That's where we met.
你可是万人迷啊
You were a bloody knockout.
回想以前的我们
Oh, it's odd, isn't it,
还真有点奇怪
thinking of us back then?
我还没二十岁 你很酷 嘴里叼根烟
I wasn't even 20, and you were so cool,with your cigarette hanging in your mouth.
来
Tell you what.
- 你要做什么  - 来嘛
- What are you doing?  - Come on.
- 我们能跳…  - 走开
- We can move the...  - Oh, bugger off!
来
Come on.
我可不想那么晚了在客厅里蹦跶
I'm not prancing around in the living room at this time of night.
♪ Stagger Lee ♪
♪ And the moon was yellow ♪
♪ And the leaves came tumbling down ♪
♪ I was standing on the corner ♪
♪ When I heard my bulldog bark ♪
♪ He was barkin' at the two men who were gamblin' in the dark ♪
♪ It was Stagger Lee and Billy ♪
手举起来 对
Over the top, yeah.
♪ Two men who gambled late ♪
♪ Stagger Lee threw seven ♪
♪ Billy swore that he threw eight ♪
♪ Stagger Lee told Billy ♪
♪ I can't let you go with that ♪
我们都老了
We ain't 20 any more.
是啊
No.
我们上楼吧
Let's go upstairs.
快来
Come on with ya.
希望我记得你做的这些
Hope I can remember what you do.
我做给你看
I'll show you.
- 怎么样了  - 我准备好了
- How are you doing down there?  - I think I'm ready.
- 要不要我在上面  - 不了 差不多了
- You don't want me to go on top?  - No, I'm nearly there.
噢 是哦
Oh, you are, too.
噢 进来了
Oh, there you go.
亲一个
A kiss.
张开眼睛
Open your eyes,
- 呃…  - 擦
- Uh...  - Oh, shit.
哎
Oh, bugger.
- 我觉得我不行了  - 我…
- I think I've lost it.- l..,
没事的
OK, OK, OK.
杰夫 没事的
Geoff, it's OK, it's OK.
还是睡觉吧
No, let's just go to sleep.
杰夫
Geoff?
你在做什么
What are you doing?
- 杰夫  - 凯特 我没事
- Geoff?  - I'm OK, Kate.
快下来 你疯了吗
Please come down. This is ridiculous.
我没事
I'm OK.
你手里拿着什么
What's that in your hand?
什么也没有
Nothing.
- 她的照片  - 我突然看见的
- Is it her?  - I found it.
骗人 你半夜爬起来找这个
You didn't find it. You went looking for it in the middle of the night
这是两码事
and that's not the same thing at all.
- 给我看看  - 不行
- Let me see it.  - No.
杰夫 我看看
Please, Geoff. Can I see it?
凯特 回去睡觉吧
Please, Kate, just go back to bed.
把照片给我看
Show me the bloody picture!
就是张照片而已
It's just a picture. It's all it is.
没什么别的意思 就是张照片
It doesn't mean anything.it's just a fucking picture.
谢谢
Thanks.
星期三
快来
Come on!
周六有人给你化妆吗
Are you getting someone to do your makeup on Saturday?
我都没想这事
I wasn't thinking of it.
我认识个女孩 很懂察言观色
I know this girl. She's very subtle.
她不是那种行为不检点的人
You wouldn't have to worry about looking like a hooker.
莎莉有个神器 能消除黑眼圈
Sally's got this amazing roll-on thing, zaps away dark circles.
可以借你用用
I'm sure you could borrow it.
我看上去很疲倦的时候 要告诉我
If I'm looking tired, you can just tell me.
那就是现在
You're looking tired.
我很好
I'm fine.
这天气真是的
Ugh, this weather.
我跟你说的都是乔治告诉我的
I'm just telling you what George said.
我不是存心让你不高兴的
I'm not trying to upset you. Really, I'm not.
我没有不高兴 你也没说什么呀
I'm not upset, but you're not telling me anything.
你就说杰夫性情乖僻
You're just saying that Geoff was in a strange mood.
乔治是这么说的
That's what George said,
杰夫有说什么吗
Did Geoff say anything?
比如
Like what?
我还在问你呢
That's what I'm asking you.
- 关于派对吗  - 不是派对的事
- About the party?  - No, not about the party.
他们大谈政事
They were talking politics.
没了
That's it?
他十分激进
Well, he was very aggressive.
我相信乔治能很好的为自己辩解
Well, I'm sure George can stand up for himself.
和以前没什么两样
He was acting like he used to.
什么意思
Meaning?
就像有次在我生日上 他一直在我朋友面前
Like that time he kept accusing me of being a fascist
说我是法西斯
in front of all my friends at my birthday
就因为我敢说撒切尔抵抗法西斯
just because I dared to say that Thatcher hadn't done such a bad job of it.
再说 我都没投票给她
I mean, I hadn't even voted for her.
凯特 哪里好笑了
It wasn't funny, Kate,
是不好笑
No.
真冒火
Very upsetting.
他总是做纳粹敬礼姿势
He kept doing a Nazi salute.
好吧 是有点好笑
All right, it was a little bit funny.
对不起
Oh, I'm sorry,
我不应该提起这事的
I shouldn't have brought it up.
你知道杰夫是怎样的人
You know what Geoff's like.
他对事总是过度热情
He gets over-passionate about things.
这不就是你爱上他的原因吗
I suppose that's why you fell in love with him.
没错
Yes.
噢 还有件事
Oh, er, there's another thing.
什么
What?
杰夫还说他不确定要不要去工作午餐会
Geoff says he's not sure that he wants to go to the works lunch.
在克劳利餐馆的
At Crawley's?
- 那不就是明天嘛  - 是啊
- But it's tomorrow.  - I know.
都组织这么久了
And it's been organised for so long,
乔治很想几个老友聚在一起 要是…
George was looking forward to getting the old gang together but if...
他有说原因吗
Well, did he say why?
没说
Don't think so.
我跟他说
I'll speak to him.
不要紧的
Er, maybe it doesn't matter.
不行 我去问他
No, I'll speak to him.
女士们
Ladies...
需要吗
Full, full?
需要加奶吗
Do you want more milk?
好
Yes.
饼干要吗
Biscuit? No?
不要吗
No?
那我放这了 我吃一块
Well, I'll leave them there. And I'll take one.
- 谢谢  - 之后
- Thank you.  - After that,
商人使用这新凿的航道
the merchants used these newly created waterways,
这些年来 航道越来越深 越来越宽
and over the years they were cut deeper and widen
布罗兹区才会是现在的模样
and this is why the Broads are as they are today
供大家观赏
for all of you to enjoy.
想想如果那些罗马人在别的地方找到泥炭
Now, just imagine if those Roman shad found peat elsewhere
或选择其他地区来开凿
or chosen to dig in another part of the country.
这片区域就不复存在了
Then these broads wouldn't be here at all.
那是杰夫吗
Is that Geoff?
没错
Yes, it is.
他在干吗
What's he doing?
怎么又抽上烟了
Is he smoking again?
是的
Look's like it.
周六前要给他剃个胡子
You should get him to shave before the big day too.
- 嗨 杰弗里 -嗨 Lena
- Hello, Geoffrey.  - Hello, Lena.
讲话准备好了吗
Hope you've got your speech prepared.
周六 说点愉快的事
I want to hear nice things about Kate on Saturday.
听说你不想去午餐会
So, I hear you don't want to go to the Crawley's lunch.
我倒是不介意 但我想知道缘由
I don't mind if you don't,but I wondered why.
就是不想去
I just don't.
你一直都想见你的工友们
You've been looking forward to seeing everyone again.
前几周你一直都在说这事儿
You've been talking about it for weeks,
- 你干吗不去  - 我自有原因
- Why don't you want to go?  - I've got me reasons.
什么原因
Which are?
我去不去和你有什么关系
Why does it matter to you if I go or not?
是没有 但都安排好了
It doesn't, but it's been arranged.
那又怎样
So?
那你也不能因为心情不好就简单拒绝不去啊
So you can't just back out of things simply because you don't feel like it.
即便你有理由
Even when you have reasons.
乔治会伤心的
And George will be very upset.
他都准备好几周了
He's...well, he's been organising it for weeks.
- 他是你朋友  - 好 我去
- And he's your friend.  - Oh, fine.
- 那你会去  - 我不是说了吗
- Then you'll go?  - Well, that's what I said, didn't I?
有天 我们忘了要去意大利的事 就呆在原地
Some days, we forgot all about getting to Italy. Just stayed put.
我们心不在焉
We were being heedless.
就是这个词
I think that's the word I'm looking for,
心不在焉
Heedless?
对
Heedless.
在柏林 柏林墙还在
Back in her Berlin, the Wall was going up
[猪湾事件：美国阴谋以武力支持古巴流亡者颠覆古巴革命政权]
在美国 我们有猪湾事件
and in America, we'd just had the Bay of Pigs.
而在那儿 我们什么都不想
But up there, we weren't thinking about all that.
不想未来
Weren't thinking about our future.
同时 我们也十分谨慎
But, at the same time,we weren't heedless at all.
知晓你的目标 每天活得都有目的
How can you be when,when you know what your purpose is?
你怎么还能心不在焉呢
When every day seems to have some point to it.
找到居所 找到食物
Finding somewhere to stay, finding food.
我们不出去的日子
And the days we didn't go anywhere,
充满目标
they seemed just as purposeful
就像我们早上四点出发一样 满心目标
as when we set out in complete seriousness at four in the fucking morning.
我觉得 这就是衰老最糟之处
I-I think, um.., I think that's the worst part of getting decrepit,
失去生活的意义
losing that...purposefulness,
我记得今天种花时的场景
I-I was remembering today how we used to seed these flowers.
是紫罗兰吧
Some sort of violet, I think they were.
在雪融之处找一块草
They'd find a patch of grass where the snow had melted
它们就能迅速生长
and they'd just spring up.
我知道它们就是花 可十分决然
I know they were only flowers, but they seemed so determined.
甚至有点勇敢
Brave, even.
我也是这样看我和卡蒂亚的
And that's how I see Katya and me.
游走四方 远离尘嚣
Wandering around, turning our backs on civilisation.
很勇敢
Brave?
可以这么说
In a way.
你不觉得吗
Don't you think?
没觉得
Not really.
为什么
Why not?
你们都做了些什么
I mean, what were you actually doing?
你们不就是爬山吗
You're just climbing up some bloody mountain.
我不是说我们的行为是勇敢者的做法
Well, I'm not saying what we did was out of bravery.
我觉得这就是你情我愿的事
I think you were just chasing a girl who wanted to be chased.
你不了解她
You didn't know her.
是的
No.
我不了解她
I didn't.
我累了
I'm tired.
睡之前 我先问你点事
I want to ask you something before we go to sleep.
什么
What's that?
如果她还活着 你们也到了意大利
She hadn't died, you had got to Italy,
你会娶她吗
would you have married her for real?
可我们没去成啊
But we didn't get to Italy, did we?
而她也死了
And she did die.
没错 但如果呢
Yeah, but if you had.
你不是讨厌假定问题吗
I thought you didn't like theoretical questions.
回答我
Just answer me.
我会娶她
Yes.
你会娶她
Yes, you would have married her?
是的
Yes.
我们会结婚
We would have married each other.
以后不能在谈及她的事了
I don't think I can talk about her any more.
我虽然说过 但我做不动
I know I said I could, but I can't.
星期四
有认识的人吗
Anyone you know still there?
什么 没有 都是新来的
What? No, they're all new.
那行 晚点见
OK, then, I'll see you later.
好
Yeah.
等会儿
Hang on.
今天尽量玩的开心点
Just try and enjoy yourself today.
我尽量
Yeah. I'll try.
你好
Hello.
- 是默瑟夫人吗  - 是的
- Mrs Mercer?  - Yes, it is.
嗨 我是DJ乔治
Hi, it's George the DJ.
噢 我也想给你打电话
Oh, yes, I-I meant to call you,
我需要周六的歌单
I need the songs for Saturday.
歌啊 噢
Er, song? Oh, songs, yes,
等一下
Er...just a minute.
- 海龟乐队的“Happy Together”  - 品味不错
- "Happy Together" by The Turtles.  - OK good choice.
水牛城斯普林 · 菲尔德的《For What It's Worth》
"For What It's Worth" by Buffalo Springfield.
马文 · 盖伊的《Um, Your Precious Love》
"Um, Your Precious Love" by Marvin Gaye.
还有《Higher And Higher》
And "Higher And Higher" by...
我忘了是谁的歌了
I don't remember who that's by.
是杰基 · 威尔逊吗
Is it Jackie Wilson?
没错
Yeah.
- 埃尔顿 · 约翰的《Your Song》如何  - 不要他的
- What about "Your Song" by Elton John?  - No. No Elton John.
还有 我都准备好歌单
What else? I-I haven't got my list.
穆迪 · 布鲁斯
The Moody Blues?
够了
That's enough.
那第一支舞的歌呢
What about your first dance?
The Platters的《Smoke Gets In Your Eyes》
"Smoke Gets In Your Eyes" by The Platters.
谢谢 麻烦了 再见
Yeah, thank you. Thank you so much.Goodbye.
怎么样
How was it?
没完没了
Fucking endless.
难以相信 他们如此糟蹋这地方
You wouldn't fucking believe what they've done to the place.
现在都成流水线了
It's all been streamlined.
我的第一份饭碗都不存在了
My first job on the floor doesn't exist any more.
要是我在管理层 我绝对不容许这样的事发生
I tell you, if I was still in management,I wouldn't have let that happen.
工会一点也不在乎
And the unions, they don't give a shit.
或者他们有所作为 也没人鸟他们
Well, maybe they do and nobody takes any notice.
小伙子们都老了 不帅了
A-And how the lads have descended into old age, it's not pretty.
乔治他一直在说他那个尤克里里
And there's George,waning on about his fucking ukulele.
最糟的是 其他人还很感兴趣的样子
The worst part of it is that they all seemed interested.
还有莱恩 他在葡萄牙有个别墅
And Len, he's got a villa on the Algarve.
还记得红头莱恩吗
Do you remember Red Len?
我们都叫他Len-in
We used to call him Len-in,
现在他说的都是在葡萄牙打高尔夫
and now all he can talk about is playing golf on the AI-fucking-garve
和他那当银行家的孙子
with his grandson, who's a banker.
红头莱恩有个当银行家的孙子
Red Len, with a banker for a grandson.
真操蛋
Fuck me!
星期五
[我自己坐公交去镇上了，抱歉！]
下午好 能耽误几分钟吗
Good afternoon, love. Spare a couple of minutes?
能给您介绍一下我们的慈善项目吗
I'd love to tell you a bit about this charity we've got going on.
不太感兴趣
Um, I'm not interested.
没关系的
No? No problem.
有什么能帮您的吗
Can I help you?
- 能坐下说吗  - 当然
- May I sit down?  - Yeah, please do.
- 想去哪儿旅行呢  - 我不是…
- Is there somewhere you have in mind?  - No, I...
我就想知道一个男的来过没有
I want to know if a man has been in here.
我丈夫
It's my husband.
我们参加过几次你们旅行社 我想知道他来过没
We've used you a few times and I wondered if he'd been in.
咨询去瑞士的那位先生
Um, was he enquiring about Switzerland?
- 怎么去了这么久  - 对不起
- Been a long time.  - Yeah, sorry.
我去…
I've been...
镇上很挤 回来的公交也…
Well, town was very busy and the bus back was... Sorry.
今天我去了趟旅行社
I went to the travel agent today.
- 哪儿  - 旅行社
- What?- I went to the travel agent.
你打算去瑞士
Are you going to Switzerland?
- 没有  - 干嘛不去
- No. I'm not.  - Why not?
不中途坐下休息 我连村庄都到不了
Well, I can't walk to the village without... without sitting down.
我还爬什么山啊
How am I going to climb a fucking mountain?
就因为这个
And that's the reason?
凯特 这不是原因
No, Kate, that's not the reason.
要是你真的去了 我…
Because if you do go, and if I,..
凯特 这跟卡蒂亚没关系
Oh, Christ, Kate. This isn't about Katya.
求你 不要说她的名字
Please, Stop saying her name.
- 我受不了  - 这跟卡蒂亚没关系
- I can't bear it.  - It isn't... It isn't about Katya.
有关系
It is.
当然脱不了干系
Of course it is.
我发现屋子里总有股味道
Like me discovering what this smell is around the house.
- 别这样  - 是她的香水味吧
- Oh, please.  - And it's her perfume, OK?
好像他一直在墙角那站着
It's like she's been standing in the corner of the room all this time,
- 就在我身后  - 别瞎说
- behind my back.  - Oh, come on.
玷污一切
And it's tainted everything.
我们的决定 去哪儿度假 看什么样的书
All our decisions, where we go on holiday, what books we read,
养什么样的狗 听什么样的音乐
what dog you want to choose, what music we want to listen to.
大事也归她管
And the big things, too.
特别是这些事
Especially the big things.
这些都不关她的事
She's had nothing to do with any of that.
我想跟你说我脑子里的事
I'd like to be able to tell you everything I'm...thinking,
我知道的一切
and everything I know,
但我做不到
but I can't.
我明白这种感受吗
Do you understand that?
明白
Yeah.
我明白
Yes, I do.
我现在只想你明天能赴约
All I want now is for you to just come to the party tomorrow.
- 我当然会去  - 我要你的心也去
- Of course I'm going to come.  - I really need you to want to be there.
我是真心的
Yes, I do want to be there.
我知道 我满足不了你
Because it's one thing me knowing. I haven't been enough for you.
这…
It's something...
凑在一起就变味了 大家也看在眼里
altogether different that everyone else feels it, too.
你觉得你满足不了我
You really believe you haven't been enough for me?
不是 我觉得我做到了
No. I think I was enough for you,
我不确定你也这么想
I'm just not sure you do.
凯特 哎
Ah, Kata.
不要这么想
That's terrible.
- 今天吃药的吗  - 还没
- Have you taken your pills today?  - No.
那我去帮你拿
Then I'm going to get them.
然后我们照常吃饭 睡觉
And then we're going to have dinner, and then we're going to go to bed.
当什么也没发生 照常起床
And then we're going to get up.
我们试着重新开始
And we'll try and start again.
凯特 可以 我能做到
OK, Kate, I can do that.
我们可以的
We can do that.
我保证
I promise.
星期六
早上好
Morning.
我给你泡了茶
I made you some tea.
我修好抽水马桶了 还没伤到手
I've managed to fix the lavatory without cutting me finger off.
起晚了吗
Is it late?
我想做点炒鸡蛋
Y-Yeah, I thought I'd make us some scrambled eggs
然后我们带马克斯去散步
and then we can take Max for a walk.
- 好  - 就这样
- Great.  - Right.
马上就来
Will do.
我们还有鸡蛋吧
Yeah, we have got some eggs, haven't we?
在我我看到过一只旋木雀 一种可爱的小鸟
I saw a tree creeper here,once, a lovely little bird.
人们说 它会飞到树的底部 然后再飞上去
Somebody told me that they fly down to the bottom of the tree and work their way up.
而五子雀 喜欢从上飞到下
And nuthatches, they fly to the top of the trunk, work their way down.
来来 好孩子
Come on. Come on. Good boy.
- 你以前很喜欢观鸟  - 是啊
- You used to love your birdwatching. -I did, yes.
你却忘记了那些让你快乐的事 多好笑啊
It's funny how you forget the things in life that make you happy.
马克斯 呆在这
Stay there, Max.
找到了 马克斯
Found it, Max.
对不起 没给你准备礼物
Again, I'm sorry. I didn't get you anything...
别傻了
Oh, don't be silly.
很漂亮
This is very beautiful.
很高兴你喜欢
I'm glad you like it.
本来想给你买块表的
I was going to get you a watch.
想刻字的 但没想好刻什么
I was thinking of having it engraved, but I wasn't sure what to write.
不要刻时间就好
I like not knowing the time.
- 我就是做不到  - 是的
- I just couldn't do it.  - No.
亲爱的 别担心 没人逼你  - 大多数人都不想做的
- Don't worry, darling, you don't have to.  - Most people don't want to.
跟我来 带你看样东西
Will you come with me? I've got something to show you.
莱娜 我不想要惊喜
No surprises, Lena. I don't want a surprise.
- 哇  - 不错吧
- Wow.  - Isn't it wonderful?
看看
Look at this. Yes.
- 莱娜 那是什么  - 过来看看
- Lena, what's that?  - Ah, come and have a look.
照片
Photos.
- 哪找来的  - 我从大伙那儿搜刮来的
- Where did they all come from?  - I rang round. Everyone contributed.
大多数都是我的
Most of them are mine.
凯特 看 你多美啊
Look, Kate, look how beautiful you are.
凯特 泰莎小狗时的样子
Kate. There's Tessa when she was a puppy.
还有我瞪着眼睛 再剪草
Ah, there's me...me and me goggles,strimming
剪草
Strimming.
- 看我们 还记得吗  - 埃及之旅
- Look at us there. Remember that?  - Egypt.
对 我们去埃及的时候
Yeah, when we went to Egypt.
我们都好美
Gorgeous, we both are.
莱娜 这太好了 谢谢
Lena, this is wonderful. Thank you.
我这个法西斯做的不错吧
Not bad for an old fascist, huh?
很不错
Yeah, not bad at all.
- 我等着听你说话呢  - 都在脑子里
- Oh, I can't wait to hear your speech.  - Yeah, it's all in here.
- 那我们就麻烦了  - 特别是你
- Ugh, we're all in trouble then.  - Yeah, especially you.
等着看那些眼泪吧
Just you wait for those tears.
- 那是谁  - 是Arthur吧
- Who's that?  - That's Arthur, I think.
- 对对  - 是他
- Yes, it is.  - Yes.
- 是几年后的他  - 我看看还有谁
- Yeah, it's Arthur, a few years ago.  - And who else do I see?
女士们先生们 大家期待已久的时刻到了
Ladies and gentlemen, the moment you've all been waiting for.
掌声有请 杰弗里 默瑟先生
I give you...Mr Geoffrey Mercer.
去吧 杰弗里
Go on, Geoffrey.
听得见吗
Now, can you hear me?
- 听得见  - 好
- We can hear you.  - Yes.
我尽量不说胡话
I'd better try and make sense, then.
感谢大家今天能到场
Well, I'd like to thank you all first, offer being here this evening.
一些人会想起我的心脏手术
Some of you may recall that, er...my bypass,
几年前抢了风头 不管怎样 我们现在还在
er, upstaged things a few years ago, so. anyway, there we are.
我不怎么做这种讲话
Now, er, I'm not used to making this kind of speech
也不会在这种场合讲话
on this, er...sort of occasion,
但…
but, er...well...
我尽力吧
I'll give it me best shot.
我们慢慢变老
As, um, as we get older.
我们就不再做决定
We seem to stop, er, making choices.
那种影响人生的决定
Big ones. anyway.
人一生中这样的决定可能是有限的吧
Perhaps we only get so many, er, in a lifetime,
用尽了 就不会再有
and once we've used them up, they're gone.
或者是我们的脑子腐朽陈旧了
Or maybe our brains, they just get a bit, er, old and arthritic,
像乔治的膝盖一样
like, er.,.like George's knee.
就这样吧
Er, whatever.
年轻时所做的决定
The upshot is that the choices we make when we're young
会影响你的一生
are pretty bloody important.
就像凯特和我做的决定
Er, like the choice, er,Kate and me made
四十五年前的今天
45 years ago...today_
就是今天
Today.
事情也不都是如桃花源记般悠闲自得
Now, things... things haven't always been, er.,.idyllic.
和普通夫妻一样 我们也有兴衰沉浮
Er, like all couples, we've had our downs as, er,..as well as our ups.
我们都想…
We all, we all, er, think...
要是能换一种方式做事 就好了
W-We all wish we'd done some things,er, differently,
要是不犯错就好了
wish we hadn't made certain mistakes,
但是
but, er...whatever...
我得说 我必须要说
I have to say, and I need to say,
凯特 说服你嫁给我
that persuading you, er, to marry me, Kate,
是我做的最有意义的事
was the best thing I've ever done.
当然也是下了不少功夫的
Er, it took some doing, by the way.
你父亲 我还是觉得
Yeah, so your father, I-I don't think he was convinced
他认为让你嫁给我是委屈了你
I was the greatest catch in the world.
我在想这是为什么
I wonder why that was.
不管这些了 说服你嫁给我
But anyway, er, persuading you to many me
是我做的最有意义的事
was the best thing I've ever done,
对不起 我真的
and, er, I'm sorry, I truly am,
你都不知道…
that, er, you haven't, er... you haven't always known that
对我来说 凯特…
because, er, well, for me, Kate,
这就是今天派对的原因
this is, er, this is what it's... what it's all about, what all this is about,
大家…我们的朋友都欢聚一堂的原因
why all... why all our friends are here this evening.
是因为你和我
It's about, er... it's about you and me.
凯特 是因为你和我
You and me, Kate.
我们的故事
Us.
是的
Yeah.
我就说这么多了
And I think, really,that's about all I've, er... got to say,
还有 我爱你
except that, er... l love you.
我真的很爱你
I love you very much.
感谢你容忍了我这么多年
And thank you for standing by me through all these years
忍受我的胡言乱语 愿我们的爱情长存
and putting up with all my nonsense, and, er... long may it continue.
杰夫和凯特
Geoff and Kate!
太棒了
It was fantastic. Wasn't it?
是的
It was.
现在…
And now...
让小两口来跳他们的第一支舞吧
Would the two lovebirds kindly take to the floor for the first dance?
我再插一句话
And for those of you that don't know, or weren't alive,
这是四十五年前他们婚礼时放的同一支歌
this is the very same song that was played 45 years ago today.
有请默瑟夫妇
I give you Mr and Mrs Mercer.
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 ♫
♪ Smoke Gets In Your Eyes ♪
♫ 人们曾经问我怎知 ♫
♪ They asked me how I knew ♪
♫ 我的爱情意真挚 ♫
♪ My true love was true ♪
♫ 噢 ♫
♪ 0h! ♪
♫ 我理直气壮地回答 ♫
♪ I of course replied ♪
♫ 内心深处的感情 ♫
♪ Something here inside ♪
♫ 是无法否认的 ♫
♪ Cannot be denied ♪
♫ 他们说总有一天你会发现 ♫
♪ They said some day you'll find ♪
♫ 恋爱中的人都是盲目的 ♫
♪ All who love are blind ♪
♫ 噢 ♫
♪ 0h! ♪
♫ 当你热情澎湃的时候 ♫
♪ When your heart's on fire ♪
♫ 你才会意识到 ♫
♪ You must realise ♪
♫ 你的眼睛蒙上了一层烟雾 ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your eyes ♪
♫ 我嘲笑他们 这令我发笑 ♫
♪ So I chaffed them and I gaily laughed ♪
♫ 想到他们竟怀疑我的爱 ♫
♪ To think they could doubt our love ♪
♫ 如今我的爱人离我而去 ♫
♪ Yet today, my love has flown away ♪
♫ 我终于失去了我的爱 ♫
♪ I' I am without my love ♪
♫ 失去了我的爱 ♫
♪ Without my love ♪
♫ 饱受朋友的讥笑 ♫
♪ Now laughing friends deride ♪
♫ 伤心的泪水再也隐藏不住 ♫
♪ Tears I cannot hide ♪
♫ 噢 ♫
♪ 0h! ♪
♫ 我只能强颜欢笑地说 ♫
♪ When a lovely flame dies ♪
♫ 当爱情的火焰熄灭时 ♫
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your eyes Smoke gets in your eyes ♪
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your eyes ♪
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的… ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your... ♪
♫ 眼 ♫
♪ Eyes ♪
♫ 我们已经说了 ♫
♪ We've already said ♪
45周年
♫ 再见 ♫
♪ Goodbye ♪
♫ 既然你一定要离开 ♫
♪ Since you've got to go ♪
♫ 噢 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ Oh, you'd better go now ♪
♫ 去吧 去吧 去吧 ♫
♪ Go now, go now, go now ♪
♫ 在你看见我哭泣之前 ♫
♪ Before you see me cry ♪
♫ 我不想你告诉我 ♫
♪ I don't want you to tell me ♪
♫ 你现在想要做什么 ♫
♪ Just what you intend to do now ♪
♫ 因为 我得告诉你多少次 ♫
♪ 'Cause how many times do I have to tell you ♪
♫ 亲爱的 亲爱的 我现在依然爱你？♫
♪ Darling, darling, I'm still in love with you now? ♪
♫ 我们已经说了… ♫
♪ We've already said... ♪
♫ “再见” ♫
♪ "So long" ♪
♫ 我不想看见你离开 ♫
♪ I don't want to see you go ♪
♫ 喔 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ Oh, you'd better go now ♪
♫ 去吧 去吧 去吧 ♫
♪ Go now, go now Go now ♪
♫ 你连试都不要试 ♫
♪ Don't you even try ♪
♫ 告诉我你并不想这样离开 ♫
♪ Telling me that you really don't want me to end this way ♪
♫ 因为 亲爱的 亲爱的 ♫
♪ 'Cause, darling, darling ♪
♫ 你难道看不出我想要你留下？♫
♪ Can't you see I want you to stay? ♪
♫ 啊 ♫
♪ Yeah ♪
♫ 既然你一定要离开 ♫
♪ Since you've got to go ♪
♫ 噢 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ Oh, you'd better go now ♪
♫ 去吧 去吧 去吧 ♫
♪ Go now, go now Go now ♪
♫ 在你看见我哭泣之前 ♫
♪ Before you see me cry ♪
♫ 我不想你告诉我 ♫
♪ I don't want you to tell me ♪
♫ 你现在想要做什么 ♫
♪ Just what you intend to do now ♪
♫ 因为 我得告诉你多少次 ♫
♪ 'Cause how many times do I have to tell you ♪
♫ 亲爱的 亲爱的 我现在依然很爱你 ♫
♪ Darling, darling, I'm still in love ♪
♫ 依然很爱你 ♫
♪ Still in love with you now ♪
♫ 我不想看见你离开 ♫
♪ I don't want to see you go ♪
♫ 可是亲爱的 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ But, darling, you'd better go now ♪